We're so close to having
a functional chatbot. We
started with loading documents, then
we split them, then
we created a vector store, we
talked about different types of retrieval,
we've shown
that we can answer questions, but we
just can't handle follow-up questions, we can't
have a real conversation
with it. The good news is, we're
going to fix that in
this lesson. Let's figure out how.
We're now going to finish
up by creating a
question answering chatbot. What
this is going to do is, it's going
to look very similar to before, but we're
going to add in this concept of
chat history. And this is
any previous conversations
or messages that
you've exchanged with the
chain.
What that's going to allow it to do, is
it's going to allow it to
take that chat history
into context when it's trying to
answer the question. So if you're
asking a follow-up question, it'll know what
you're talking about.
An important thing to
note here is that
all the cool types
of retrieval that we
talked about up to this point,
like self-query or compression or
anything like that, you
can absolutely use them here. All
the components we talked about are
very modular and can fit together
nicely. We're just
adding in this concept
of chat history.
Let's see what it looks like. First, as
always, we're going to load our
environment variables.
If you have the platform set up,
it might also be nice to
turn it on from the beginning.
There'll
be a lot of cool things that we'll want
to see what's going on
under the hood.
We're going to load our
vector store that has
all the embeddings for
all the class materials.
We can run through basic similarity
search on the vector store.
We can initialize the
language model that we're
going to use as our chatbot. And
then, and
this is all from before, which
is why I'm skimming
through it so quickly. We can
initialize a prompt template, create a
retrieval QA chain, and then
pass in a question and
get back a result.
But now let's do more. Let's add
some memory to it. So we're going to
be working with conversation
buffer memory. And what
this does is it's just going to
simply keep a list, a buffer of chat
messages in history, and it's going to
pass those along with the question
to the chatbot every
time.
We're going to specify memory key, chat
history. This is just going to line
it up with an input
variable on the prompt. And
then we're going to specify return messages
equal true. This is
going to return the
chat history as a
list of messages as opposed to a single
string. This is
the simplest type of memory. For a
more in-depth look at memory, go back to
the first class that I
taught with Andrew. We covered it
in detail then.
Let's
now create a new type of chain, the
conversational retrieval chain. We
pass in the language model, we
pass in the retriever, and
we pass in memory. The
conversational retrieval chain
adds a new bit on top of the retrieval
QA chain, not just memory.
Specifically, what it adds is
it adds a step
that takes the history
and the new question
and condenses it into a stand-alone
question to pass to
the vector store to
look up relevant documents.
We'll take a look at this in
the UI after we run it
and see what effect it has. But
for now, let's try it out. We can
ask a question. This is
without any history, and see
the result we get back. And then
we can ask a follow-up question to
that answer. This is the
same as before. So we're asking, is probability
a class
topic? We get some answer.
The instructor assumes that
students have basic
understanding of probability
and statistics. And
then we ask,
why are those prerequisites
needed? We get back a
result, and let's take a look at
it. We get back an answer,
and now we can see that the answer
is referring to basic probability and
statistics as prerequisites
and expanding upon
that, not getting
confused with computer
science as it
had before.
Let's take a look at what's going
on under the hood in the UI. So here,
we can
already see that there's a bit
more complexity. We can see
that the input to the
chain now has not only
the question, but also chat
history. Chat history is
coming from the memory, and this gets
applied before the chain is invoked
and logged in this logging system.
If we look
at the trace, we can see
that there's two separate things
going on. There's first a call
to an LLM, and then there's a call
to the stuff
documents chain.
Let's take a look at the first call. We
can see here a prompt with some instructions.
Given
the following conversation, a
follow-up question, rephrase the
follow-up question to
be a stand-alone question. Here, we
have the history
from before. So we have the
question we asked first, is probability a class
topic? We then have the
assistance answers. And then out here,
we have the stand-alone
question. What is the reason for
requiring basic probability and statistics as
prerequisites for the
class?
What happens is that stand-alone
answer is then passed
into the retriever, and
we retrieve four documents
or three documents or
however many we specify. We
then pass those documents
to the stuff documents
chain and try to
answer the original question. So
if we look into that, we
can see that we have the system answer,
use the following pieces of context
to answer the user's question.
We've got a
bunch of context. And then we
have the stand-alone question down below.
And then we get
an answer. And here's the answer that is
relevant for the question at
hand, which is about probability and
statistics as prerequisites.
This is a good time
to pause and try out
different options for this chain.
You can pass in different prompt
templates,
not only for answering the question,
but also for rephrasing
that into a stand-alone question. You
can try different types of memory, lots
of different options to
pull out here. After this, we're going
to put it all together
in a nice UI. There's going to
be a lot of code for
creating this UI, but this is
the main important bit
right here. Specifically, this is
a
full walkthrough of basically this
whole class. So we're going
to load a database and retriever
chain. We're going to pass in
a file. We're going to load it with
the PDF loader. We're then going to load it
into
documents. We're going to split those documents. We're
going
to create some embeddings and put
it in a vector store.
We're then going to turn that
vector store into a retriever. We're
going to use similarity here
with some "search_kwargs=k", which we're
going to set equal
to a parameter that we can
pass in. And then we're going to
create the conversational retrieval chain. One important
thing to note here
is that we're not
passing in memory. We're going
to manage memory externally for the
convenience of the GUI
below. That means that
chat history will have to
be managed outside the
chain.
We then have a lot more code here.
We're not going to spend too
much time on it, but
pointing out that here we're passing
in chat history into
the chain. And again, that's because
we don't have memory attached
to it. And then here we're
extending chat history with the result. We
can then put it
all together and run this to get a
nice UI through which we can interact with
our chatbot.
Let's ask it a question. Who
are the TAs? The
TAs are Paul Baumstarck, Catie
Chang.
You'll notice here that there's a
few tabs that we can also click
on to see other things. So if
we click on the database, we can
see the last question we
asked of the database, as well
as the sources we got back
from the lookup there. So these
are the documents. These are
after the splittings
happened. These are
each chunk that we've retrieved. We
can see
the chat history with the input
and the output. And then there's
also a place
to configure it where you can
upload files.
We can also ask follow-ups. So let's ask,
what are their majors? And we
get back an answer about the
previously mentioned TAs. So we
can see that Paul is studying machine learning
and computer vision, while
Catie is actually a
neuroscientist.
This is basically the end of the class.
So now's a great time to pause, ask
it a bunch more questions, upload
your own documents here, and
enjoy this end-to-end question answering
bot, complete with an
amazing notebook UI.
And that brings this class on LangChain,
chat with your data, to an end.
In this class, we've
covered how to use
LangChain to load data
from a variety of
document sources using LangChain's 80-plus
different document
loaders. From there, we
split the documents into chunks and
talk about a lot of the nuances that
arrive when doing so.
After that, we take those chunks,
create embeddings for them,
and put them into a vector store,
showing how that
easily enables semantic search.
But we also talk about some of the
downsides of semantic search
and where it can
fail on the certain
edge cases that arise.
The next thing that
we cover is retrieval,
maybe my favorite part of the class,
where we talk about a lot of new
and advanced and really
fun retrieval algorithms for
overcoming those edge cases.
We combine that with
LLMs in the next session,
where we take
those retrieved documents,
we take the user question,
we pass it to an LLM,
and we generate an
answer to the original question.
But there's
still one thing missing, which
is the conversational
aspect of it.
And that's
where we finish out the class, by
creating a fully functioning end-to-end chatbot
over your data. I've really enjoyed teaching
this class. I hope you guys
have enjoyed taking it. And I want to
thank everyone in the open source who has
contributed a lot of
the things that make
this class possible, like
all the prompts
and a lot of the functionality that you
see.
As you guys build
with LangChain and discover
new ways of doing
things and new tips and techniques,
I hope that you share what you'll
learn on Twitter or even open
up a PR in LangChain.
It's a really fast-moving field, and it's
an exciting
time to be building.
Look forward to seeing everything.